In the last few videos, we
ここ何回かのビデオで、
talked about a collaborative filtering algorithm.
協調的フィルタリングのアルゴリズムについて議論してきた。
In this video I'm going to
このビデオでは、このアルゴリズムの
say a little bit about the
ベクトル化した実装について
vectorization implementation of this algorithm.
ちょこっと話しておきたい。
And also talk a little bit about other things you can do with this algorithm.
またついでにこのアルゴリズムについて出来るその他の事についても話す。
For example, one of the
例えば、出来る事の一つに
things you can do is, given
ある商品が
one product can you find
与えられた時に、
other products that are related
これに関連した商品を探す、
to this so that for
というのがある。これは例えば
example, a user has recently been looking at one product.
ユーザーが最近ある商品を見たとすると、
Are there other related products
このユーザーに推薦する、別の関連した
that you could recommend to this user?
商品は無いか？という事。
So let's see what we could do about that.
ではどうやってこれが出来るか見てみよう。
What I'd like to do is work
ここでやろうとしているのは、
out an alternative way of
協調的フィルタリングのアルゴリズムの予測を
writing out the predictions of the collaborative filtering algorithm.
別のやり方で練習する、という物。
To start, here is our
はじめに、これが
data set with our
我々のデータセットで
five movies and what I'm
五つの映画がある。
going to do is take
そして私がやる事は、
all the ratings by all the
ユーザーのレーティングを全て
users and group them into
取ってきて、一つの行列に
a matrix. So, here we have
グループ化する。するとここでは、
five movies and four
5つの映画と4人のユーザーがいるので、
users, and so this
この行列yは
matrix y is going to be
5x4行列になる。
a 5 by 4 matrix. It's just you know, taking all
これは単純に、
of the elements, all of this data.
これらの要素、これらのデータを全部とってきて、
Including question marks, and grouping them into this matrix.
これははてなマークも全部含めて、それをこの行列にグループ化した物だ。
And of course the elements of this
もちろんこの行列の要素、
matrix of the (i, j) element of
この行列の要素 i jは、
this matrix is really what
実際は、以前に
we were previously writing as y
yの上付き添字i jと
superscript i, j. It's
書いていた物だ。
the rating given to movie i
それはユーザーjによる映画iのレーティング。
by user j. Given this
我らの持つ全てのレーティングを含む
matrix y of all the
この行列Yが与えられたとすると、
ratings that we have, there's
レーティングを予測する
an alternative way of writing
アルゴリズムを書き下す
out all the predictive ratings of the algorithm.
代替的な方法がある。
And, in particular if you
特に、もしあなたが
look at what a certain
あるユーザーのある映画に対する
user predicts on a
予測を調べたいなら、
certain movie, what user j
ユーザーjの映画iに対する予測の
predicts on movie i is given by this formula.
式はこうなる。
And so, if you have
だから、予測されたレーティングの
a matrix of the predicted
行列があれば、
ratings, what you would
それは以下のような
have is the following
行列だろう、
matrix where the i, j entry.
i jエントリが
So this corresponds to the rating
これがユーザーjが映画iに
that we predict using j
与えるレーティングの
will give to movie i
予測値で、
is exactly equal to that
それは正確に
theta j transpose
シータjの転置 xi にイコールだ。
XI, and so, you know, this is a matrix
つまり、この行列は、
where this first element
最初の要素、
the one-one element is a
この要素 1 1は、
predictive rating of user one
ユーザー1の映画1に対するレーティングの
or movie one and this
予測値だ。
element, this is the one-two
そしてこの要素、要素 1 2は、
element is the predicted rating
ユーザー2の映画1に対する
of user two on movie
レーティングの予想値。
one, and so on,
などなど。
and this is the
そしてこれは、
predicted rating of user one
ユーザー1の最後の映画に対する
on the last movie and
レーティングの予想値。
if you want, you know,
そしてこれは、
this rating is what we
このレーティングは
would have predicted for this value
この値を予想した物で、
what we would have predicted for that
この値を予想した物で、、、
value, and so on.
などなど。
Now, given this matrix of
いま、このレーティングの予想値の行列が
predictive ratings there is then
与えられたとすると、これらを書きだす
a simpler or vectorized way of writing these out.
より簡単な、またはベクトル化した方法が存在する。
In particular if I define
まず、行列Xを
the matrix x, and this
定義する。これは、
is going to be just
以前、線形回帰であった
like the matrix we had earlier for linear regression to be
行列に似ている。
sort of x1 transpose x2
x1の転置にx2の転置に、、、と
transpose down to
xのn mの転置まで
x of nm transpose.
降りていく。
So I'm take all the features
つまり全ての映画の
for my movies and stack
フィーチャーを持ってきて
them in rows.
列として積んでいく。
So if you think of
つまり各映画を
each movie as one example
一つの手本とみなして、
and stack all of the features
それら別々の映画のフィーチャーを
of the different movies and rows.
列として積んでいく訳だ。
And if we also to
そしてまた、
find a matrix capital theta,
行列として大文字のシータも作りたい。
and what I'm going to
その為には、
do is take each of
ユーザー毎のパラメータベクトルを
the per user parameter
取ってきて、
vectors, and stack them in rows, like so.
同様に列として積んでいく。
So that's theta 1, which
つまり、これがシータ1で、
is the parameter vector for the first user.
これは最初のユーザーのパラメータベクトルだ。
And, you know, theta 2, and
そしてシータ2、
so, you must stack
つまり、このように
them in rows like this to
列として積んでいって
define a matrix capital
大文字のシータの行列を定義する。
theta and so I have
するとこのように列として積み上がった
nu parameter vectors all stacked in rows like this.
n u個のパラメータベクトルを列に持った物を得る。
Now given this definition
さて、行列Xと行列シータが
for the matrix x and this
こう定義
definition for the matrix theta
されたとして、
in order to have a
全ての予測を計算する
vectorized way of computing the
ベクトル化した方法を
matrix of all the predictions
得るには、
you can just compute x times
単純に X掛けるシータ転置 を
the matrix theta transpose, and
計算するだけで良い。
that gives you a vectorized way
それがここにあるこの行列を計算する
of computing this matrix over here.
ベクトル化した方法となっている。
To give the collaborative filtering
協調的フィルタリングには、
algorithm that you've been using another name.
別の名前もある。
The algorithm that we're using
我らの使っているこのアルゴリズムはまた、
is also called low rank
低ランク行列分解とも
matrix factorization.
呼ばれている。
And so if you hear
つまりもし人々が
people talk about low rank matrix
低ランク行列分解について
factorization that's essentially exactly
話しているのを耳にした時は、それは本質的には
the algorithm that we have been talking about.
我らがここまで議論して来た物と同一の物だ。
And this term comes from the
そしてこの用語は
property that this matrix
この行列 X 掛ける シータ転置 が持つ
x times theta transpose has a
数学的特徴に、
mathematical property in linear
線形代数では
algebra called that this
この低ランク行列と
is a low rank matrix and
呼ばれる物があって、
so that's what gives
だからこれらのアルゴリズムには
rise to this name low
低ランク行列分解という
rank matrix factorization for these
名前がついた。
algorithms, because of this low
この行列 X シータ転置 の持つ低ランクという
rank property of this matrix x theta transpose.
行列の特徴の為に。
In case you don't know what
もし低ランクというのが
low rank means or in case you don't
なんなのか知らなくて、低ランク行列というのが
know what a low rank matrix is, don't worry about it.
何なのか知らなくても、まぁ気にすんな。
You really don't need to know that in order to use this algorithm.
このアルゴリズムを使うのに、そんな事を知ってる必要はまったく無い。
But if you're an expert in
だがもしあなたが線形代数のエキスパートなら、
linear algebra, that's what gives
そんな理由でこのアルゴリズムに
this algorithm, this other name
低ランク行列分解という
of low rank matrix factorization.
別名がついた、というワケ。
Finally, having run the
最後に、協調的フィルタリングのアルゴリズムを
collaborative filtering algorithm here's
実行する時に、
something else that you can do
実行出来る別の事として、こんなのがある。
which is use the learned
それは関連する映画を探す為に
features in order to find related movies.
学習したフィーチャーを用いる、という物。
Specifically for each product i
具体的には、各商品iに関して
really for each movie i, we've
実際には各映画iに関して、
learned a feature vector xi.
フィーチャーベクトルxiを学習した。
So, you know, when you learn a
つまり、あるフィーチャー群を学習した時には、
certain features without really know
どんなフィーチャーがあるのかとかは
that can the advance what the
前もっては
different features are going to be, but if you
知らなかった。
run the algorithm and perfectly the features
だがアルゴリズムを実行すると、フィーチャーは
will tend to capture what are
これらの別々の映画の
the important aspects of these
または別々の商品の、またはなんでも、
different movies or different products or what have you.
これらの重要な性質は何か、を捕捉する傾向にある。
What are the important aspects that cause
何がある種のユーザー達がある映画たちを
some users to like certain
好きになる重要な
movies and cause some users
特徴なのか、そしてあるユーザー達が
to like different sets of movies.
異なる映画を好む、重要な特徴とは何か。
So maybe you end up
だから例えば、最終的に
learning a feature, you know, where x1
あなたはフィーチャーx1としてロマンスを
equals romance, x2 equals
x2としてアクションを、これまでの例と同様に
action similar to
学習した上で、
an earlier video and maybe you
さらに別のフィーチャーx3として
learned a different feature x3 which
コメディー度合いを
is a degree to which this is a comedy.
学習する事になるかもしれない。
Then some feature x4 which is, you know, some other thing.
さらにx4として別の何かを学習するかも。
And you have N
そうやってn個のフィーチャーを
features all together and after
得る事になったとして、
you have learned features it's actually often
実際はこれらのフィーチャーを
pretty difficult to go in
見ていって、これらのフィーチャーが
to the learned features and come
本当は何を意味しているのかを
up with a human understandable
人間が理解するのは
interpretation of what these features really are.
とても難しい事が多い。
But in practice, you know, the
だが実践的には、
features even though these features can be hard to visualize.
これらのフィーチャーが、たとえ可視化する事すら大変でも、
It can be hard to figure out just what these features are.
これらのフィーチャーが何なのかを突き止めるのは大変であっても、
Usually, it will learn
だいたいは、それが何にせよ
features that are very meaningful
あなたが映画を好いたり嫌ったりする
for capturing whatever are the
もっとも特徴的でとても意義深い
most important or the most salient
特徴を
properties of a movie
捕捉しているフィーチャーを
that causes you to like or dislike it.
学習する。
And so now let's say we want to address the following problem.
では、以下のような問題に取り組むとしよう。
Say you have some specific movie
あなたがある映画iを持ってたとする、
i and you want
そしてあなたはその映画に
to find other movies j
関連した別の映画jを
that are related to that movie.
探したい。
And so well, why would you want to do this?
ところで、いったいなんでそんな事したいのか？
Right, maybe you have a
いいでしょう。例えば
user that's browsing movies, and they're
ユーザーが映画をブラウズしているとする、
currently watching movie j, than
そして彼は今、映画jを観ているとする、
what's a reasonable movie to recommend
その時、映画jを観終わった後に
to them to watch after they're done with movie j?
彼に視聴を推薦すべき、リーズナブルな映画はなんだろう？
Or if someone's recently purchased movie
または誰かが映画jを購入したとすると、
j, well, what's a different
その時に彼らに購入を検討してもらう為に
movie that would be reasonable to recommend to them for them to consider purchasing.
推薦する事がリーズナブルな別の映画はなんだろう？
So, now that you have
いまやあなたはこれらの学習した
learned these feature vectors, this gives
フィーチャーを持っているのだから、
us a very convenient way to
これを用いて二つの映画がどの位近いかを
measure how similar two movies are.
測るとても便利な方法がある。
In particular, movie i
具体的には、映画iは
has a feature vector xi.
フィーチャーベクトルxiを持つ訳だが、
and so if you can find
別の映画jを、
a different movie, j, so
フィーチャーベクトル xiとxjの
that the distance between
距離が短い物として
xi and xj is small,
探す事が出来る。
then this is a pretty
これは二つの映画、
strong indication that, you know, movies
iとjが類似しているという
j and i are somehow similar.
極めて強い示唆を与える。
At least in the sense that some of them
少なくとも、映画iを好きな人は
likes movie i, maybe more likely to like movie j as well.
映画jも好むだろう、という意味において。
So, just to recap, if
ではまとめると、
your user is looking
ユーザーが映画iを
at some movie i and if
見ていたとする、
you want to find the 5
そしてあなたはその映画にもっとも似た
most similar movies to that
5つの新しい映画を彼らに
movie in order to recommend
リコメンド（推薦）
5 new movies to them, what
したいとする。
you do is find the five
あなたがする事は、これら別々の映画間で
movies j, with the
フィーチャーの距離が一番小さい
smallest distance between the
5つの映画を
features between these different movies.
探してくる、という事。
And this could give you a few different movies to recommend to your user.
これであなたは勧めるべき幾つかの映画を得る事が出来る。
So with that, hopefully, you
以上で全てのユーザー、全ての映画の
now know how to use
予測レーティングを
a vectorized implementation to compute
ベクトル化して実装し計算する
all the predicted ratings of
やり方を
all the users and all the
理解出来ただろう、
movies, and also how to do
そして学習したフィーチャーを
things like use learned features
どのように用いて、
to find what might be movies
どの映画とか商品が
and what might be products that aren't related to each other.
関連しているのかを探す方法も。